Well, here we are again in Google Colab.
さて､ グーグルコラボに再びやってきた｡
It's been a minute since we were here, and welcome back to it.
ここに来るのは久しぶりだが､ おかえりなさい｡
Uh, this week we're going to spend our time here and it's going to be terrific.
あー､ 今週はここで過ごすことになるんだけど､ すごいことになりそうだよ｡
It's actually it's going to be the best week yet.
実際､ これまでで最高の週になりそうだ｡
I know I keep saying that, but this time it really, really is going to be peak peak.
何度も言うようだが､ 今回は本当に､ ピークがピークになりそうだ｡
The only thing that's going to be better than what we do here is what's coming next week in week eight,
ここでやっていることより良くなりそうなのは､
which really, I mean, I can't wait to tell you about that.
来週の第8週だ｡
But stay focused, keep on week seven.
だが､ 集中を切らさずに7週目を続けてくれ｡
There's a lot to go through here.
ここには通過しなければならないことがたくさんある｡
So first we do.
だからまず､ そうしよう｡
I've set up this week seven day one Colab.
この週7日目のコラボをセットアップした｡
We start with some installs.
まずはインストールから始めよう｡
Um, and one of the things we're installing is a new package you've not seen before, a hugging face
PeftはParameter Efficient
library called Peft, which stands for parameter efficient fine tuning, parameter Efficient Fine Tuning,
Fine Tuningの略で､ ローラを含むライブラリの名前だ｡
Uh, it's within this library.
この図書館の中にあるんだ｡
Pfft, pfft.
プッ､ プッ｡
Just rolls off the tongue.
舌を巻く｡
Um, so that is it.
ええと､ それで終わりです｡
I am on a T4 box, which is the lowest of the GPU boxes, which just has 15, gigabytes of GPU Ram.
私は､ GPUボックスの中で最も低いT4ボックスを使用しており､ 15ギガバイトのGPUラムを搭載しているだけだ｡
You can see, most of which I'm already using up just a few cells into this.
見てわかるように､ ほんの数セルを入れただけで､ そのほとんどをすでに使い切っている｡
So anyway, we do our Pip installs.
とにかく､ 僕らはピップをインストールするんだ｡
We do a bunch of imports here, uh, and set some constants.
ここではたくさんのインポートを行い､ いくつかの定数を設定する｡
We're going to be working with a base model which is llama 3.18 billion.
ベースモデルはラマ3だ｡  180億ドル
And I'm also setting a fine tuned model here.
そして､ 私はここで微調整モデルも設定している｡
I obviously we haven't done any fine tuning yet.
まだ微調整はしていない｡
I'm.
私は｡
This is from the future.
これは未来から来たものだ｡
Uh, I'm bringing this in just so I can show you what a fine tuning model looks like in terms of the
ラウラ・マトリックスがターゲット・モジュールに適用されるファインチューニング・モデルがどのようなものかをお見せするために持ってきたんだ｡
And then here are three hyper parameters which now you're an expert on are which I am setting to 32.
そして､ ここに3つのハイパーパラメーターがある｡
You probably remember I said start with eight and then go to 16 and then go to 32.
8から始めて16､ 32と言ったのを覚えているだろう｡
Well I got to 32.
32歳まで来たよ｡
Uh, and that was where I ended up.
結局､ そこに行き着いたんだ｡
Uh, and so I'm doing 32 here.
それで､ ここで32をやっているんだ｡
Uh, alpha is a rule of thumb, double R.
ええと､ アルファは経験則で､ ダブルRだ｡
So there it is at 64.
それで64点だ｡
And the target modules.
そしてターゲット・モジュール｡
So these are the four names of the layers that we are targeting.
これが､ 私たちがターゲットにしている4つのレイヤーの名前だ｡
And you will see why shortly.
その理由はすぐにわかるだろう｡
And this is by far the most common, uh, setup for llama models.
そして､ これがラマ・モデルの最も一般的なセットアップだ｡
Other models may have different names of their layers, but yeah, you give the names of the layers
他のモデルではレイヤーの名前が違うかもしれないが､ そう､ ターゲットモジュールに割り当てるこのリストに､
that you will be targeting in this list that you assign to target modules.
ターゲットとするレイヤーの名前を与えるのだ｡
Okay.
オーケー｡
So next, this is some standard stuff that you've done a few times now to log in to Hugging Face.
次に､ これはハギング・フェイスにログインするために何度かやったことのある標準的なものだ｡
Um, and I've got the usual blurb that if you don't have hugging face account, but of course you have
ええと､ もしあなたがハグする顔のアカウントを持っていないなら､ もちろんあなたは今頃ハグする顔のアカウントを持っているでしょう､
a hugging face account by now.
といういつもの宣伝文句があります｡
Uh, but you log in there, it's free, you get a token, and then you go to this section in the Colab,
でも､ そこでログインして､ 無料だし､ トークンももらえるし､ それからColabのこのセクションに行って､
the, the key, and you use that to put in your, uh, your, your token, um, as you've done in the
キーというのを使って､ トークンを入れるんだ｡
past.
そうすれば､ このセルを走らせれば､ ハギング・フェイスにログインできる｡
Uh, the alternative is you could just type in your token there.
トークンを入力することもできる｡
If you have any problems with accessing the notebook.
ノートブックへのアクセスに問題がある場合｡
Okay, so without further ado, I am going to read in the base model without any quantization.
さて､ それでは早速､ ベースモデルを量子化せずに読み込んでみよう｡
No funny business.
おかしなことはしない｡
We're just going to read in the entire llama 3.18 billion base model, remembering that is the smallest
ラマ3世を全部読むだけだ｡  180億円のベースモデルは､ リャマ・シリーズの最小モデルであることを忘れてはならない｡
Uh, device map equals auto means use a GPU if you've got one which which this box does.
ええと､ デバイス・マップ・イコール自動というのは､ GPUがあればそれを使うということです｡
And I'm not going to run this now because I just ran it and it took about five minutes.
そして､ 私は今これを実行するつもりはない｡
Uh, and it came up with a warning that it couldn't fit it all in GPUs.
ええと､ GPUに全部は入りきらないという警告が出たんだ｡
So some of it went on the CPU.
だから､ その一部がCPUに使われたんだ｡
And that's why if you look at the resources over on the right, you'll see that my GPU is 11 out of
右側のリソースを見ると､ GPUは15ギガのうち11ギガが埋まっていて､
15 gigs are filled up, and almost 13 gigs of Ram are also filled up.
ラムも13ギガ近く埋まっている｡
So it's really taken up both the reason for the spike here is because I did it once, and then I restarted
だから､ ここでの急上昇の理由は､ 一度やって､ 再開してまたやったからだ｡
Uh, obviously all you will see is the the one rise up to the top when you run this.
ええと､ これを実行すると､ 明らかに1がトップに上がるのが見えるだけです｡
Okay.
オーケー｡
And so now I'm going to print how much memory is this base model using up.
では､ このベースモデルのメモリ使用量をプリントしてみよう｡
And again if you if you wanted to train this it would it would take many many more times.
そしてまた､ もしこれをトレーニングしようと思ったら､ 何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も何度も｡
This this is just how much memory is the base model using up, and its memory footprint is just north
これは､ ベースモデルがどれだけのメモリーを使用しているかということであり､ そのメモリーのフットプリントは32GBのすぐ北にあり､
of 32GB, 32GB of memory being used.
32GBのメモリーが使用されている｡
And you may remember that's what we said earlier.
以前､ 私たちがそう言ったことを覚えているだろう｡
It's basically 32 bit floats for each of the 8 billion parameters.
基本的には､ 80億の各パラメーターに対して32ビットの浮動小数点数だ｡
Okay.
オーケー｡
So that's, uh, it's big.
だから､ それは大きいんだ｡
Uh, and let's just look at it.
ええと､ ちょっと見てみましょう｡
You can just take a look by printing the base model itself.
ベースモデルそのものをプリントして見ることができる｡
And this now is a view on what it looks like, um, so briefly before, but we'll just pause for a moment.
そして､ これは今､ どんな風に見えるかというと､ うーん､ 前に簡単に書いたけど､ ちょっと小休止｡
And again, this isn't going to be a deeply theoretical class, so I'm not going to do too much in the
繰り返しになるが､ これは深く理論的な授業になるつもりはないので､ できることを言う以外にはあまり説明するつもりはない｡
What is made clear when you look at the architecture of this neural network is that there are it consists
このニューラルネットワークのアーキテクチャーを見れば明らかなように､
embeds it into vectors in the in the neural network.
まず埋め込み層がある｡
So this is very it's like the, the encoder encoding LMS that we talked about before.
つまりこれは､ 前に話したLMSをエンコードするエンコーダーのようなものだ｡
The first layer is embedding tokens, um, into a, um, a vector.
最初の層は､ トークンumをベクトルumに埋め込む｡
Uh, and in fact, that is the dimensionality of how many possible tokens we have.
実際､ これが可能なトークンの数の次元なんだ｡
And this is the dimensionality of the embedded vectors.
そして､ これが埋め込まれたベクトルの次元数である｡
So there are then 32 layers called Lama decoder layers.
そのため､ ラマ・デコーダー・レイヤーと呼ばれる32のレイヤーが存在する｡
32 sets of them.
32セットだ｡
And each of those 32 looks like all of this.
そして､ その32人はそれぞれこのように見える｡
Let's get that right to there.
それを正しく伝えよう｡
Um, and so you can you can go through this, but you can see that it consists of the the set of attention
このレイヤーは､ q､ proj､ k proj､ v､ o projと呼ばれるアテンション・レイヤーのセットで構成されています｡
And these these are the layers that we have targeted in our target modules, which is typically what
そしてこれらのレイヤーは､ ターゲット・モジュールでターゲットにしたレイヤーである｡
you do.
他の方法も試すことができるが､ これが最も一般的な方法だ｡
And you'll see that, uh, some of these layers have 4000 odd dimensions in and out.
そして､ これらのレイヤーのいくつかは､ 4000の奇妙な寸法が出たり入ったりしているのがわかるだろう｡
Uh, this one and this one and some of them are 4000 in and and 1000 out.
ええと､ これとこれと､ いくつかは4000人入って1000人出ている｡
So they've got some different dimensionality there.
だから､ 彼らには次元の違うものがある｡
And that will be somewhat relevant when we look at the lora A and Lora B.
そしてそれは､ ローラAとローラBを見るときに多少関係してくる｡
But I'm not going to get too deep into this, but this is yours to experiment with and read up on if
しかし､ 私はこのことについてあまり深入りするつもりはない｡
There is then a multi-layer perceptron layer with something that, for example, the the up is something
そして多層パーセプトロン層があり､ 例えば､ アップは次元数を爆発的に増やし､
that explodes out the number of dimensions, and then the down then reduces down the number of dimensions.
ダウンは次元数を減らす｡
And that's followed by an activation function.
そしてその後に活性化関数が続く｡
Again, for people that are more familiar with this stuff.
繰り返しになるが､ こういうことに詳しい人たちのために｡
The activation function that's used for Lama is Selu, which you can see in the PyTorch documentation.
Lamaに使われている活性化関数はSeluで､ PyTorchのドキュメントで見ることができる｡
You can look at it and learn more about what that is and and why it is used.
それを見て､ それが何なのか､ なぜ使われるのか､ もっと詳しく知ることができる｡
Um, so that is then followed by by layer norm layers.
ええと､ だから､ その後にレイヤー・ノルム・レイヤーが続く｡
Um, and then at the very end there is a linear layer, the LM head.
そして一番最後にLMヘッドという直線的な層がある｡
And this is sometimes targeted.
そして､ これは時に標的にされる｡
This is sometimes added to target modules.
これはターゲットモジュールに追加されることもある｡
As I mentioned before, in the cases where you wanted to generate something, where part of what you
前にも述べたように､ 何かを生成したい場合､ 学習させたいことの一部が結果を生成することである場合､
want it to learn is to generate results, that will take a different format of some sort.
それは何らかの別の形式を取ることになる｡
Maybe you want a particular structure of JSON, or maybe something completely different, like you want
JSONの特定の構造が必要かもしれないし､ まったく別のものが必要かもしれない｡ たとえば､
it to speak a different language, or you want it to to structure things in some, some very unique
別の言語を話させたいとか､ 非常にユニークな方法で物事を構造化させたいとか｡
Then you might target this in your target modules as well.
それなら､ ターゲットとするモジュールでも､ これをターゲットにするかもしれない｡
Um, but that gives you a sense of the architecture.
うーん､ でもこれで建築の雰囲気はわかるよね｡
And in a second, when we look at the Lora adapters, you'll see why I've taken a moment to dwell on
そしてすぐに､ ローラのアダプターを見れば､ なぜ私がこのことに時間を割いたのかがわかるだろう｡
All right.
分かった｡
So we used up 32GB.
それで32GBを使い切った｡
The next thing we need to do is to restart this session by going to runtime and restart session to clear
次に必要なのは､ このセッションを再起動することだ｡ ランタイムからセッションの再起動を実行し､ メモリーをクリアにして続行できるようにする｡
There are some torch commands that will clear the cache, but in fact they're not aggressive enough.
キャッシュをクリアするトーチコマンドはいくつかあるが､ 実際には十分な攻撃性はない｡
It still holds on to too much because we've consumed so much.
私たちが多くのものを消費してきたせいで､ まだ多くのものを抱えている｡
The only way forwards now is to restart the session.
今はセッションを再開するしかない｡
So that's what I'll do.
だから､ そうするつもりだ｡
And I will see you in the next video once I have restarted and I'm back here again.
また次のビデオでお会いしましょう｡